I am aware that I am inhaling, I am aware that I am exhaling, I am following my
breath, I am aware of my body, I release my body, I generate
a feeling of joy, I generate a feeling of happiness in
the present.
I acknowledge my pain, I embrace my pain, I take care of it.
It is important to have a good motivation when you start to meditate.
It will present you with obstacles. The first obstacle you
will encounter is laziness. It will
bring you a second subtlety, that is called active laziness. I ended up doing a
lot of things except meditate. A third laziness that arises is
abandonment. But
then you say to yourself, no, ultimately it's not for me. The antidote is to find
the right motivation.
This motivation must be
not only for yourself, but also for others.
The second real obstacle you will encounter,
is that when you learn to meditate,
at first, there is a methodology in learning.
The obstacle you will face is the complete forgetfulness of what to do.
At one point, I was doing meditation,
well, I thought I was meditating,
I was sitting there, after all, I was daydreaming quite a bit.
I realized that meditation is training the mind.
It comes from a very ancient etymology that means...
truly learning to discover one's own workings.
You are not always well when you meditate, but that's okay.
I learn to recognize, to train my mind.
And the antidote, which I think is very interesting for us in the practice of meditation,
is attention, it is mindfulness.
Discovering that energy within your mind, that energy which is concentration,
and which will gradually open you up to another energy that is deep insight into things.
But you must go slowly.
It’s like entering a space where there are walls.
There are secrets that can be revealed.
I enter with a candle, and the candle is your mind.
At first, the candle flickers, which means there isn’t much light.
But if through the practice of your meditation, the foundation, you learn to completely stabilize the flame,
there will be a kind of luminous halo that appears, a kind of clarity that emerges.
Well, it’s a bit the same.
If you really manage to stabilize your mind, suddenly you will perceive a sort of
luminous clarity.
that appears in your mind. This clarity leads you to deep vision.
You need to learn
to stabilize the mind because it is all about the work of stabilization. So
it’s about learning
to develop this clarity of mind through first the energy of mindfulness,
the energy of concentration, and the energy of deep insight.
You need to
train. Everyone can access this.